Guide to the Michael Latham papers, 1950-2010.
Latham, Michael papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Michael Latham papers, 1950-2010.
29-2-3928
Latham, Michael C.
40 cubic feet.
Correspondence, printed materials, publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, publications, reports, and subject files concerning Latham's work as a professor in the Division of Nutritional Sciences and his work in international nutrition.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor emeritus in the Division of Nutritional Sciences, Cornell University from 1968-2004 and Director of the Cornell Program in International Nutrition for 25 years.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, publications, reports, and subject files concerning Latham's work as a professor in the Division of Nutritional Sciences and his work in international nutrition, focusing on breastfeeding, infant and child health; parasitic infections and their relationship to health, nutrition, human rights and the World Health Organization.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Latham, Michael C.; Latham, Michael C.; Cornell University -- Faculty.; Cornell University. Graduate School of Nutrition.; World Health Organization.
Subjects:
Diet -- Africa.; Breastfeeding -- Africa, Sub-Saharan.; Breastfeeding -- Developing countries.; Infants -- Nutrition.; Infants -- Nutrition -- Study and teaching; Lactation -- Study and teaching -- Developing countries.; Advertising -- Baby foods -- Developing countries.; Nutrition.; Mothers.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical
Box 31
Series II. Correspondence
Box 1-14, 35, 36
Series III. Conference Papers, Consulting Reports, Lectures – in chronological order
Box 15-25
Series IV. Course Material
Box 31-35
Series V. Subject Files
Box 26-31, 36
Series VI. Publications
Box 27,37, 38
Series VII. Visual Images, Cassette Tapes, Films
Box 36
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical
  - Vitae, 1963-2002 (Box 31, Folder 17)
  - Publication Lists, 1968-1995 (Box 31, Folder 18)
  - Biographical Information, 1970s-2009 (Box 31, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Annual Reports, 1978-1992, 2001 (Box 31, Folder 20)
  - Michael Latham Celebration-25 Anniversary as Director of the Cornell Program in International Nutrition, 1993 (Box 31, Folder 21-22)
  - "The Right to Food and Good Nutrition"-Transcript, Cassette Tapes and Video (2 copies) (#6261), 1993 (Box 31, Folder 23)
  - Michael Latham Celebration, 1996 (Box 31, Folder 24)
  - Biography of Graduate Students Who Majored in International Nutrition with Michael Latham, July 1970-December 2003 (Box 31, Folder 25)
  - Institute for African Development-Advisory Committee, 2002-2009 (Box 31, Folder 26)
  - 40 Plus Years of International Nutrition Research and Advocacy- Conducted by Michael Latham and his Colleagues and Students, 2008 (Box 31, Folder 27)
  - Five Decades of International Nutrition Research and Advocacy Conducted by Michael Latham, 1963-2002 (Box 31, Folder 28)
  - CINAR Reception - photos, 2008 (Box 31)
- Series II. Correspondence-Boxes 1-14 are restricted and contain correspondence with former students and colleagues - in alphabetical order by last name
  - A-B, 1969-2007 (Box 1)
  - C-Jac, 1969-2007 (Box 2)
  - Jel-N, 1969-2007 (Box 3)
  - Nov-W, 1969-2007 (Box 4)
  - W-Z and A-B, 1969-2007 (Box 5)
  - Bru-Eic, 1969-2007 (Box 6)
  - E-Grei, 1969-2007 (Box 7)
  - Grew-J, 1969-2007 (Box 8)
  - K-L, 1969-2007 (Box 9)
  - M-Ms, 1969-2007 (Box 10)
  - Mt-Pin, 1969-2007 (Box 11)
  - Po-Sc, 1969-2007 (Box 12)
  - Se-T, 1969-2007 (Box 13)
  - Th-Z, 1969-2007 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Fan Mail, 1975-1995 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, January-May 1981 (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, June-December 1981 (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 35, Folder 15-16)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 35, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 35, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 35, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1986 (Box 35, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1988-2007 (Box 35, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence-World Alliance for Breastfeeding Action (WABA), 2002 (Box 35, Folder 22-24)
  - Letters of Inquiry about the M.P.S. Degree-A-H, 1972-1974 (Box 35, Folder 25)
  - Letters of Inquiry about the M.P.S. Degree-J-Z, 1972-1974 (Box 35, Folder 26)
  - National Dairy Council-Correspondence, Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 35, Folder 27)
  - National Dairy Council-Correspondence, Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - National Dairy Council-Correspondence, Reports, 1975-1977 (Box 36, Folder 2)
- Series III. Conference Papers, Consulting Reports, Lectures, Trip Reports – in chronological order
  - July 1966-January 1973 (Box 15)
  - February 1973-November 1974 (Box 16)
  - December 1974-January 1978 (Box 17)
  - February 1978-November 1983 (Box 18)
  - December 1983-April 1985 (Box 19)
  - June 1985-March 1987 (Box 20)
  - April 1987-February 1990 (Box 21)
  - August 1990-February 1992 (Box 22)
  - March 1992-March 1993 (Box 23)
  - September 1993-June 1995 (Box 24)
  - November 1995-2009 (Box 25)
- Series IV. Course Material
  - NS 306-Final Exams, 1967-2002 (Box 31, Folder 29)
  - NS 680-International Nutrition Problems, Policy and Programs-Lectures, 1977-1998 (Box 31, Folder 30)
  - NS 680-Course Material (Box 31, Folder 31-32)
  - NS 680-Protein Energy Malnutrition, 1970s-2007 (Box 31, Folder 33)
  - NS 680-Protein Energy Malnutrition-Resource Material, 1970s-1990s (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
  - NS 680-Malnutrition and Mental Development, 1960s-1970s (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - NS 680-Iodine Deficiency Disorders (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - NS 680-Protein Energy Malnutrition, 1970s-1980s (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - NS 680-Nutrition and Infection-Resource Material, 1970s-1990s (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
  - NS 680-Iron and Nutrition Anemias-Resource Material (Box 32, Folder 8-10)
  - NS 680-Dental Caries and Fluroide-Resource Material (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - NS 680-Zinc and Child Health-Resource Material, 1997 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - NS 680-Vitamin A Lectures (Box 32, Folder 13-15)
  - NS 680-Vitamin A-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - NS 680-Control of Micronutrient Deficiencies-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - NS 680-Famine-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 3-4)
  - NS 680-Viamin B Deficiencies-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - NS 680-Vitamin C and Scurvy-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - NS 680-Vitamin D and Rickets-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - NS 680-Growth Monitoring-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - NS 680-Monitoring Children's Health, Nutrition Rehabilitation-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 9-10)
  - NS 680-Diarrhoea-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - NS 680-Health Services-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 12-14)
  - NS 680-Nutrition Surveys and Surveillance-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 15-17)
  - NS 680-Food Habits-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - NS 680-Recommended Dietary Allowances-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - NS 680-Nutrition Education and Training-Resource Material (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - NS 680-Nutrition Policy-Resource Material (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
  - NS 680-Protein Rich Foods-Resource Material (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - NS 680-Enrichment and Fortification-Resource Material (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - NS 680-Well-Being and Worker Productivity-Resource Material (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - NS 680-NGOs and United Nations Agencies-Resource Material (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - NS 680-Nutrition Diseases and Affluence-Resource Material (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - NS 680-Selected Readings, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 8-9)
  - NS 680-Exams, Take Home Assignments (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - NS 680-Nutrition Diseases and Affluence-Resource Material (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - NS 300-International Agriculture-Lecture, 1997-2006 (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - NS 306-World Food and Nutrition Problems in Perspective-Lecture, 1997 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - NS 306-Severe Malnutrition-Lecture, 2006 (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - NS 306, 1969-2001 (Box 34, Folder 15-17)
  - NS 695-Holistic or Targeting Interventions, 1979 (Box 34, Folder 18)
  - NS 660-International Service Learning, 2007 (Box 34, Folder 18A)
  - School of Nutrition Lecture-Case Studies, 1969 (Box 34, Folder 19)
  - School of Nutrition Lecture-School Feeding, 1969 (Box 34, Folder 20)
  - School of Nutrition Lecture-Legislation, 1969 (Box 34, Folder 21)
  - School of Nutrition Lecture-Pica, 1969 (Box 34, Folder 22)
  - School of Nutrition Lecture-Fish Farming, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 23)
  - School of Nutrition -Hunger and Malnutrition in the United States, 1969-1970 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - School of Nutrition-Malnutrition in the United States-Resource Material, 1968-1974 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Lectures in the Philippines (Box 34, Folder 3)
- Series V. Subject Files
  - Breastfeeding-Correspondence, Articles, Reports, Publications, 1972-2002 (Box 26)
  - Breastfeeding-Talks, Reports, Publications and Conference Proceedings, 1970-2004 (Box 27)
  - Testimony-United States Senate on Nutrition and Human Needs, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Testimony on Cereal Controversy, 1970-1972 (Box 28, Folder 2-9)
  - Testimony-Food Commodity Program, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 10-12)
  - Testimony-National Advisory Review Board-Sugar Hearing, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Testimony-Puerto Rico Food Stamp Litigation, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Testimony to United States Senate - Mission in Sahel Africa, 1973-1975 (Box 28, Folder 15-20)
  - Testimony-Federal Trade Commission Hearing on Trade Regulation and Rules on Food Advertising, 1976 (Box 28, Folder 21)
  - Testimony and Proceedings-FTC vs. California Milk Producers Advisory Board, 1978-1979 (Box 28, Folder 22)
  - Testimony-Hearing of Barcelo Commission on Free Speech, March 1987 (Box 28, Folder 23)
  - Research Ideas, no date (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Comparative Histories of Rickets and Kwashiorkor, no date (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Harvard- Malnutrition and Mental Health, no date (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Tanganyika Subject Files, 1960s (Box 29, Folder 2-5)
  - Policies and Plans for Food and Nutrition Programs, 1963 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Nutritional Studies in Tanzania-Latham and Stare, 1965 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - W.E.E.I. Radio, 1965 (Box 30, Folder 57)
  - Articles/Letters Concerning IUDs, 1966 (Box 30, Folder 58)
  - Mauritania Subject File, 1970s (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Hatch Grant, 1970s (Box 29, Folder 8-9)
  - Nutrition Case Studies-Book, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - WHO-Philippines-Consulting, 1969-1970 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - WHO-Philippines, Pakistan-Consulting, 1972-1973 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Pan American Health Organization Technical Advisory Committee on Nutrition, 1972 (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - Ryan Prize, 1973 (Box 29, Folder 14-15)
  - CIA Request for Proposals for Nutrition Research, 1978 (Box 29, Folder 16)
  - Ethics of Intervention Research in Populations-Latham and Habicht, 1979 (Box 29, Folder 17)
  - Bryceson Scholarship, 1981-1983 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Weaning Project-Manoff International Inc., 1985-1988 (Box 29, Folder 18)
  - Beltway Bandit Applications, 1985-1987 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Center for the Analysis of World Food Issues (CAWFI) Grant, 1987 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Consulting in East and Southern Africa-Cornell/SUNY Aid, 1987 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Academy for Educational Development, 1987-1991 (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - African Studies Certificate, 1989 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Iraq Conference Proposal, 1991 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Iraq and Gulf War, 1991-1992 (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - Current Research Information System (CRIS) Reports, 1991-2007 (Box 31, Folder 13)
  - Press Release about "Killimanjaro Tales: The Saga of a Medical Family in Africa- by Gywnneth Latham and Michael Latham, 1995 (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - WHO-United Arab Emirates-Consulting, 1998-1999 (Box 29, Folder 19)
  - WHO Filariasis Control-Global Program to Eliminate Lymphatic Filariasis, 1998-2000 (Box 29, Folder 20)
  - Nuclear Winter-Carl Sagan, 1984-1985 (Box 29, Folder 21)
  - Philippines-MSG Fortification with Vitamin A, 1988-1989 (Box 29, Folder 22)
  - Land o Lakes-Zambian Nutrition Biscuits, 2007 (Box 29, Folder 23)
  - Stationery-White House, no date (Box 29, Folder 24)
  - Meals for Millions Program, 1985-1986 (Box 29, Folder 25)
  - FASEB Meeting Presentation, 1991 (Box 29, Folder 26)
  - Australian Milk Biscuit-Study in South Africa, 2004-2005 (Box 29, Folder 27)
  - Subseries I. Cornell Files
  - Cornell Medical College and Program in International Medicine, 1970-1991 (Box 29, Folder 28)
  - Cornell Women's Studies and Program on International Development and Women, 1971-1993 (Box 29, Folder 29)
  - MIT/Cornell International Nutrition Policy Series, 1972-1973 (Box 29, Folder 30)
  - Cornell Program on Policies for Science and Technology in Developing Nations, 1973 (Box 29, Folder 31)
  - Master of Professional Studies in International Development Degree, 1974-1975 (Box 29, Folder 32)
  - Cornell Photo Policy, 1977-1987 (Box 29, Folder 33)
  - Program in International Nutrition-Cornell Students, 1978-1996 (Box 29, Folder 34)
  - CISER, 1980-1992 (Box 29, Folder 35)
  - Cornell International Agriculture Rural Development, 1980-2001 (Box 29, Folder 36)
  - Cornell Biotechnology, 1983-1993 (Box 29, Folder 37)
  - Collaborative Educational Program in Nutrition-John Hopkins and Cornell, 1984-1987 (Box 29, Folder 38)
  - Campus Code, 1985 (Box 29, Folder 39)
  - Apartheid-Faculty and Staff Against, 1984-1987 (Box 29, Folder 40)
  - South Africa-Divest, 1980-1985 (Box 29, Folder 41)
  - Cornell Rural Development Committee, 1985-1991 (Box 29, Folder 42)
  - Center for the Analysis of World Food Issues (CAWFI) at Cornell- Evaluation Report, August 1987 (Box 31, Folder 14)
  - Cornell Population and Development Program, 1989-2004 (Box 29, Folder 43)
  - Cornell Southeast Asia Program, 1990-1991 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Cornell International Student Office, 1991 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Cornell Committee on African Studies, 1991 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Cornell International Development Studies, 1992-1998 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Cornell Field of Nutrition, 1993-2003 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Cornell International Studies, 1995 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Cornell South Asia Program, 1996-2000 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - FANTA Project, 1998-1999 (Box 31, Folder 15)
  - Cornell Faculty Senate, 2002-2006 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Susan George-Cornell Lecture, 2003-2004 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Kenneth Kaunda-President of Zambia-visit, 2003 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Subseries II. Division of Nutritional Sciences (DNS) Files
  - Puerto Rican Students-TOEFL Requirements, 1979 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - DNS Seminars, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - DNS Secretarial Changes, 1991 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Nutrition Intervention and Policy Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - DNS Review, 1992 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - DNS Review, 1999 (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - DNS Faculty Retreat, 1991 (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - DNS Memos, Faculty Meetings, 1994-1999 (Box 30, Folder 18)
  - DNS Memos, Faculty Meetings, 2000-2004 (Box 30, Folder 19)
  - DNS Faculty Retreat, May 2006 (Box 30, Folder 20)
  - Subseries III. Outside Organizations
  - AAAS, 1978-1979 (Box 30, Folder 21)
  - African Medical and Research Foundation (AMREF), 1985-2001 (Box 30, Folder 22)
  - Amnesty International, 1985-1988 (Box 30, Folder 23)
  - Brown University-World Hunger Program, 1990s (Box 30, Folder 24)
  - CARE, 1993 (Box 30, Folder 25)
  - Caribbean Food and Nutrition Institute, 1980-1986 (Box 30, Folder 26)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1980s (Box 30, Folder 27)
  - Catholic Relief Services, 11975, 1985 (Box 30, Folder 28)
  - Center for Science in the Public Interest, 1974-1975 (Box 30, Folder 29)
  - Committee for the Support of Aamir Raza, 2004 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  - Committee on NGOs, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 30)
  - East-West Center- Hawaii, 1977-1994 (Box 30, Folder 31)
  - Food and Agriculture Organization, 1990-2007 (Box 30, Folder 32)
  - Ford Foundation, 1979-1988 (Box 30, Folder 33)
  - Freedom from Hunger Foundation, 1980s (Box 30, Folder 34)
  - Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition (GAIN), 2002 (Box 30, Folder 35)
  - Helen Keller International, 1992-1994 (Box 30, Folder 36)
  - Institute of Nutrition of Central America and Panama (INCAP), 1979-1987 (Box 30, Folder 37)
  - International Advisory Council of Toda, 2000-2010 (Box 30, Folder 38)
  - International Center for Research on Women, 1990s (Box 30, Folder 39)
  - International Development Research Centre (IDRC), 1984-1987 (Box 30, Folder 40)
  - International Food Policy Research Institute, 1985-2002 (Box 30, Folder 41)
  - International Union of Nutritional Sciences, 1977-1978 (Box 30, Folder 42)
  - International Society for Research on Human Milk and Lactation (ISRHML), 2000-2008 (Box 30, Folder 43)
  - National Institutes of Health, 1972-1973 (Box 30, Folder 44)
  - North American Committee of NGOs, 1974-1977 (Box 30, Folder 45)
  - Protein Advisory Group, 1973-1975 (Box 30, Folder 46)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1974-2002 (Box 30, Folder 47)
  - Rotary International, 1991 (Box 30, Folder 48)
  - Standing Committee on Nutrition (SCN) and Administrative Committee on Coordination (ACC), 1997-2002 (Box 30, Folder 49)
  - Swedish International Foundation for Science, 1990 (Box 30, Folder 50)
  - Thrasher Research Fund, 1989-2003 (Box 30, Folder 51)
  - Trinity College of Dublin, 1988-2003 (Box 30, Folder 52)
  - United Nations University-MIT Workshop, 1978-1979 (Box 30, Folder 53)
  - United Nations University Hunger and Society Working Group, 1979-1981 (Box 30, Folder 54)
  - United Nations University-Tokyo Meeting, 1981 (Box 30, Folder 55)
  - UNESCO, 1972-1987 (Box 30, Folder 56)
  - UNICEF, 1996-2002 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - United Nations University, 1987-2000 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - USAID, 1977-1992 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Wellcome Trust, 1971-1972 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - World Bank, 1986-1998 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - World Food Program, 1994-2001 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - World Health Organization, 1986-2001 (Box 31, Folder 7)
- Series VI. Publications
  - "The Tang of Tanganyika: African Journal of the 1920's and 1930's" by Gwynneth Latham (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - Reprints and includes publication list with checks next to publications that are in the collection, 1960-1989 (Box 37)
  - Reprints, including some that are not listed in the publications list, 1990-2009 (Box 38)
- Series VII. Visual Images, Cassette Tapes, Films
  - Photos for Songea Show, 1960 (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Photos of various scenes and people of Africa, 1950s-1960s (Box 36, Folder 12-16)
  - Bagota Photos, 1960s (Box 36, Folder 17)
  - Photos for Latham Manual, 1950s-1960s (Box 36, Folder 18-19)
  - Photos of students, 1970s-1980s (Box 36, Folder 20)
  - Slides-ICNND, no dates (Box 36, Folder 21)
  - Slides-Zambia - Signs of Malnutrition, no dates (Box 36, Folder 22)
  - Slides and Slide Index, no dates (Box 36, Folder 23-24)
  - 296 slides of Indonesia Applied Nutrition - UNICEF, no dates (Box 36)
  - 8 glass negatives of scenes from Africa, no dates (Box 36)
  - 23- 3 1/2 x 4" lantern slides of various charts concerning nutrition, fluorosis, school feeding, etc. in Tanzania, 1950s (Box 36)
  - Honorable E. Heath M.P.- Brighton Nutrition Congress, August 1985; tr 9329 (Box 36)
  - Dr. J.C. Cravioto- Brighton Nutrition Congress, August 1985; tr 9330 (Box 36)
  - Bottle Feeding Undervalued- Michael Latham, January 5, 1977; tr 9327 (Box 36)
  - CBS Radio Show done by Michael Latham on the Dimension on Health, no dates; tr 9328 (Box 36)
  - "Bottle Babies" a film about the tragedy of infant feeding practices in the third world. The film is 26 minutes, was directed by Peter Krieg, produced in Kenya and distributed by Unifilm, of New York City., 1975; F 472
  - Computer Data -Magnetic Tape-Labeled Henry Lee, no dates (Box 36)